Guide to the Alice Mary Baldwin Papers, 1863 - 1961
Duke University. University Archives
Alice Mary Baldwin papers 1863 - 1961
Baldwin, Alice M. (Alice Mary), 1879-1960
13.25 linear feet, Extent: 12500 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Alice Mary Baldwin (1879-1960) was a professor of history and administrator at the Woman's College of Duke University for almost 25 years. She researched and published widely, made many speeches, and served as a national advocate for women's education. The Alice Mary Baldwin Papers include correspondence, personal materials, speeches, photographs, clippings, printed materials, artifacts, and other materials documenting her personal and professional life. Major subjects include women's education, women in higher education, administration of a woman's college, vocational guidance, and employment for women. Baldwin's major research interest was the colonial clergy in the United States, and she also took an active interest in contemporary labor issues. Several organizations with which Baldwin took a major interest were the U.S. Navy Waves, the American Association of University Women, the Southern School for Workers, and the Duke University Woman's College as a whole. English.
UA.29.02.0055
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Provenance
The Alice Mary Baldwin Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1955 (A48-2121); in 1960 (A60-234); in 1965 (A65-179, A67-65); in 1966 (A66-132); in 1972 (A72-31); and in 1973 (A73-136). Items were also received as a transfer in 1969 (A48-1831).
Biographical Note
[This biography was written by the Historical Society of North Carolina after the death of Alice Mary Baldwin in 1960.]
Miss Baldwin was the eldest of the five children of the Reverend Fritz Walter and Sarah Bingham Lyman Baldwin. She was born on January 24, 1879, at Lewiston, Maine, where her father was head of the Latin School. Within a year her family moved to Massachusetts, and when she was nine years of age her father accepted the pastorate of the Trinity Congregational Church in East Orange, New Jersey, which he served until his retirement in 1915. Coming from a long line of Congregational ministers and educators, she grew up in a family environment of strong religious, moral, and educational principles.
Following her graduation from a private school in East Orange, Miss Baldwin entered Bates College in 1896, the Alma Mater of her father, and won the first prize of her class for scholarship. After one year there she transferred to Cornell University, where she earned membership in Phi Beta Kappa and graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in 1900, with a major in history. During the next two years she was a graduate student and assistant in history at Cornell. After receiving her master's degree there in June, 1902, she went on a traveling fellowship to Europe for study at the Sorbonne and research in Sweden. She also spent time in Germany and England. The subject of her master's thesis had been, "Gustavus III of Sweden: A Study in Enlightened Despotism."
In December, 1903 she began teaching French, German, and English at the Glen Ridge (New Jersey) High School. The following September she went to Fargo College, Fargo, North Dakota, as Dean of Women and Instructor in History. In addition she also taught German and American literature. She remained there only two years, going in 1906 to the Baldwin School at Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania, as Instructor of History. In 1912 she was appointed head of the Department of History, and economics was added to her teaching schedule. During these years she also studied in the graduate schools of Bryn Mawr College, Columbia University, and the University of Pennsylvania, and the Teachers College of Columbia University.
She remained at the Baldwin School until 1921, when she took a leave of absence and entered the University of Chicago to study toward the doctor's degree. She was a fellow in history, and since she was specializing under Professor Andrew C. McLaughlin, she was his assistant. Her second year there she was president of the Graduate Club.
In 1923 Miss Baldwin went as Acting Dean of Women to Trinity College in Durham, North Carolina, for the summer. She had been given an assistantship in the history department of the University of Chicago for the coming year which involved teaching. While she was at Trinity President Few invited her to accept the position of Dean of Women and Assistant Professor of History. Professor McLaughlin would have preferred that she become a permanent member of the history department at Chicago, but since he saw no possibility of a woman being added to the department in the foreseeable future, he encouraged her to accept President Few's offer. She worked out an arrangement with the University of Chicago whereby she might return to Trinity after teaching there only one semester on her assistant-ship. It was in January, 1924, therefore, that she assumed her duties as Dean of Women and began teaching history to two classes of freshman women. She was the first woman to have full faculty status at Trinity College.
When she left Chicago she had only to finish her dissertation, which was on the New England clergy and the American Revolution. This she did in time to graduate in June, 1926. Her degree was awarded magna cum laude.
In December after Miss Baldwin returned to Trinity, James B. Duke signed the indenture which provided for the expansion of that college into a major university. There was to be a co-ordinate college for women among the several colleges to comprise Duke University. In 1926 Miss Baldwin was named Dean of the Woman's College, a post she held until she retired in 1947. As dean it was her responsibility to help launch and administer the college, and to her much credit is due for the high academic and social standards which it has maintained.
Feeling that the position of a dean was strengthened by class-room and faculty connection, Miss Baldwin continued to teach a section of the introductory course in history for a number of years. Finally, however, her other responsibilities made it necessary for her to give up teaching altogether.
In addition to her duties on the campus, Miss Baldwin held numerous offices in national, state, and local organizations. Some of these organizations were: the National Association of Deans of Women, the North Carolina Association of Deans, the American Association of University Women, the League of Women Voters, the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, the North Carolina Art Society, and the North Carolina Vocational Guidance Association. She was on the Durham Advisory Council of the North Carolina Unemployment Compensation Committee, the Advisory Committee of the Southern Summer School for Workers, and a director of the Alliance for the Guidance of Rural Youth. During the second World War she served with seven other distinguished women educators of the United States on the Educational Advisory Council which worked with the Bureau of Naval Personnel in organizing and directing the WAVES. She was a member of several honorary organizations other than Phi Beta Kappa, and of the Daughters of the American Revolution and the Colonial Dames. Her professional memberships also included the American Historical Association and the National Education Association.
One of Miss Baldwin's strong interests was the Historical Society of North Carolina. She was a member of the group which revived and reorganized the Society in the fall of 1945. As stated earlier, she served as its first president after the reorganization and her tactful, energetic leadership was in no small way responsible for the successful rejuvenation of this ancient and venerable body. Her presidential address on New Light Presbyterianism delivered at Greensboro College in the fall of 1946 was a model of scholarly effort and lucid presentation. Perhaps no member of the Society was more conscientious and regular in attending meetings than she, and probably no one attended with more enthusiasm and enjoyment.
Her writings include: The New England Clergy and the American Revolution, "The Clergy of Connecticut in Revolutionary Days," "The Development and Place of the Co-ordinate College," "College Bound," and "The Woman's College As I Remember It," and contributions to various magazines and to an unpublished history of the North Carolina State Division of the A.A.U.W. At the time of her death she had almost completed a study of what women were reading in the American Colonies before 1750.
As a tribute to her work in promoting higher education for women, and in recognition of her many other achievements, the Class of 1943 of the Woman's College established the annual Alice M. Baldwin Scholarship Fund. In 1946 she was awarded the degree of Doctor of Laws by the Woman's College of the University of North Carolina, and two years after she retired Duke University bestowed the same honor upon her. In 1958 she was presented the ninth annual North Carolina Distinguished Service Award for Women by the chapter of the Chi Omega sorority at the University of North Carolina.
Except for the first year and half of her retirement, Miss Baldwin spent the remainder of her life in Durham. She continued to work as much as her health would permit in a number of the organizations with which she was affiliated. She was also active in research and writing. It was during this period that she wrote the history of the Woman's College.
Two days after her death memorial services were conducted in the Duke Chapel by her pastor, Dr. Kelsey Regen of the First Presbyterian Church (there was no Congregational church in Durham when she went there), and by her friend of many years, Dr. Hersey E. Spence, Professor Emeritus of the Duke Divinity School. Her ashes were placed in the family plot at Lenox, Massachusetts. In the memories of countless students, associates, and friends, Miss Baldwin will continue to live as a woman of gracious dignity, unquestioned integrity, and superior intellect, and characterized by a strong sense of duty, a compassion for mankind, a fine appreciation of spiritual and artistic values, and an ardent love of life and nature.
Collection Overview
The Alice M. Baldwin Papers contain materials relating to Dean Baldwin's career as an educator, historian, and administrator, especially during her tenure at Duke University. Her papers include official, personal, and professional correspondence, printed matter, photographs, clippings, and other materials concerning the development and administration of the Woman's College at Duke University, the role of women's colleges in society, and the activities of business and professional women. Correspondents include other women educators, administrators of government offices and charitable and social organizations, former students, and Duke University faculty and staff. Among the major subjects besides the Woman's College are the Southern School for Workers, Inc., North Carolina and Southern labor issues, the U.S. Navy Waves program, and the education of women in general. The collection is organized into several series. The first series, Personal, includes documents related to Baldwin's family, genealogy, and education. The second series, Correspondence, consists of materials concerning her research and publications as well as general correspondence. Major correspondents include Nora C. Chaffin, Charles C. Crittenden, Katherine E. Gilbert, Meta Glass, Orie L. Hatcher, Louise McLaren, and Belle Rankin. The series is organized chronologically.
The third series, the Alphabetical File, is the largest series of the collection, and consists of professional and personal correspondence, student papers, and the office files of Baldwin. The file is arranged alphabetically by subject. Among the organizations Baldwin had an interest in were the American Association of University Women, the Institute of Women's Professional Relations, the National Association of Deans of Women, and the North Carolina Council of Women in Education. She also served on the boards of various state and federal commissions and committees dealing with the role of women's colleges in society. Her participation in the U.S. Navy Waves program is well-documented, as is her interest in the Southern School for Workers and other progressive organizations. The fourth series is Writings, which includes final versions, drafts and notes for a number of monographs and articles. Included are extensive notes from her graduate research on New England clergy. Of particular interest in this series is a 90-page manuscript, "The Woman's College As I Remember It," Baldwin's account of her hiring as the first woman with faculty rank at Duke, and the academic challenges involved in the establishment of the Coordinate College for Women there.
The fifth series is Speeches and Addresses, and is comprised primarily of notecards used by Baldwin in making presentations to a variety of groups. The next series is Photographs, and includes photographs of a European trip and excursions to the New England shore, as well as other personal photos. The sixth series is Clippings, and includes clippings on churches, labor relations, and prohibition. The following series is Printed Materials, and consists of several bound volumes, including the "Baldwin Annual" of the Baldwin School, dedicated to Alice Mary Baldwin, and J.B. Rhine's New World of the Mind, dedicated to Baldwin by the author. The final series, Artifacts, consists of two pins given to Baldwin Delta Gamma Kappa and Phi Beta Kappa, and a key from Duke University's White Duchy.
Arrangement Note
The original order of the Alice Mary Baldwin Papers was maintained whenever possible. Items were placed in series in chronological or alphabetical order. Oversized materials have been placed in oversized boxes; they are noted in the finding aid.
Subject Headings
Baldwin, Alice M. (Alice Mary), 1879-1960; American Association of University Women; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Woman's College; Duke University. Woman's College -- History; New York (N.Y.). Southern School for Workers, Inc.; United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve; Clergy -- United States; Labor -- North Carolina; Vocational guidance; Women college administrators -- North Carolina; Women college administrators -- United States; Women -- Education (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Women -- Employment; Women in higher education -- North Carolina -- Durham; Clippings; Photograph album; Photographs; Speeches
Contents of Collection
- Personal, 1862-1963
  The Personal series contains materials related to Baldwin's life outside of her Duke career. It includes awards and honors, biographical information, materials pertaining to her education, family and genealogical documents, and articles, tributes, and other documents created after Baldwin's death in 1960. Other personal materials related to this series may be found in the Photographs and the Artifacts series. Baldwin's writings completed during her education are filed in the Education series. Materials are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Awards and Honors, 1946-1955, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Information, 1934-1946, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church Materials, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Composition Book in handwriting of Alice Mary Baldwin, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Education
    - Assignments, 1922-1923, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bibliographies, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Certificates and Applications, 1915-1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Congregational Clergy of New England in the American Revolution," [undated] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Examination Books, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Master of Arts Thesis, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "The Ministers of the Gospel in Revolutionary Days," August, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Notes and Clippings, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notes and Drafts, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Notes and Examination Questions, 1923, [undated] (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Notes for History 20, [undated] (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Paper written in application of fellowship, [undated] (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Reprints, [undated] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Family
    - Covenant, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Diary of Sarah L. Baldwin [mother of A.M.B.], 1877-1885 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sermon by Fritz Walter Baldwin [father of A.M.B.], January 17, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Genealogy (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
  - Memorial
    - Clippings, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Statements, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photos, Writings, and Correspondence donated by Louise Seabolt, circa 1920-1960 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Possessions of Alice M. Baldwin," [undated] (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Materials, [undated] (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1897, 1921-1960
  The Correspondence series contains chronologically arranged letters to and from Baldwin. It contains both personal correspondence with friends and professional correspondence with colleagues. This series is closely related to the Alphabetical Files series, but the Correspondence series contains only correspondence, and is classified only by date, not by name.
  - 1897, 1921-1928 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - 1932 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - 1933 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - 1936 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - January, 1937-June, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - July, 1937-December, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - 1938 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - 1939 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - January, 1940-June, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - July, 1940-December, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - January, 1941-June, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - July, 1941-December, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - January, 1942-June, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - July, 1942-December, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - 1943 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - 1944 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - January, 1945-June, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - July, 1945-December, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - January, 1946-June, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - July, 1946-December, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - January, 1947-June, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - July, 1947-December, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - 1948-1956 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - 1957-1960, [undated] (Box 5, Folder 58)
- Alphabetical Files, 1924-1958
  The Alphabetical Files series is organized by the name of the person or organization with whom Baldwin corresponded. The materials in this series were mainly collected during Baldwin's career at Duke. Topics include Duke policies and problems, especially related to the Woman's College; Baldwin's participation in national and regional professional organizations; World War II and Baldwin's participation in the U.S. Navy Waves program; Baldwin's participation in progressive organizations such as the Southern School for Workers and the Southern Conference on Human Welfare.
  - Addoms, Ruth Margery, "Science in a Woman's College," [undated] (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Address List, [undated] (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - American Association of University Women
    - Correspondence
      - 1924-1925 (Box 5, Folder 61)
      - 1926 (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - 1927 (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - 1928 (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - 1931-1934 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - 1935-1947 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - North Carolina Division, 1929-1936, [undated] (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Other Material, 1924-1934, [undated] (Box 6, Folder 69-70)
  - American Council of Guidance and Personnel Associations
    - Correspondence, 1936-1938 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Other Materials, 1936-1939 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - American Council on Education - War Service Opportunities, 1942-1943 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - American Council on Education - War Service Opportunities, 1942-1943 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Balayan, Beatrice, 1934-1942 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Bibliographies, [undated] (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Brinkley, Roberta Florence, 1948-1958 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Business and Professional Women's Club
    - Correspondence
      - 1930-1944 (Box 7, Folder 79)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 7, Folder 80)
    - Other Material, circa 1930s - 1940s (Box 7, Folder 81-82)
  - Chapter Scholarship Committee [Delta Kappa Gamma], 1934-1953 (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Chicago University, History Department, [undated] (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - China's Children Fund, Inc., 1939 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - "College Bound" [Pamplet for Rural Girls]
    - 1934-1936 (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - 1937 (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - 1938-1945 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Council of Guidance and Personnel, 1940-1946 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Craighead Ministers, [undated] (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Duke University
    - Centennial Celebration, Women's Symposium
      - 1938 (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - January, 1939-February, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 93)
      - March, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 94)
      - April, 1939-1940, [undated] (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - Committee of the Co-Ordinate College for Women, 1925-1931, [undated] (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Committee on Intellectual Cooperation [between Duke and UNC], 1934-1937 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Committee on Promotion of Student Scholarship, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Committees, 1928-1932, [undated] (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - Conference on Education as Guidance, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - Council on Education for Women
      - 1925-1945, [undated] (Box 9, Folder 101)
      - Minutes, 1930-1943 (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - Council on Undergraduate Teaching, 1936-1942, [undated] (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - Duke Players, 1934-1947 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Educational Research Committee, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - EKO-L, circa 1936 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Explorer's Club, circa 1931-1938, 1964 [includes photographs] (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Faculty, 1944-1947 (Box 10, Folder 108)
    - Fine Arts Department, 1928-1942, [undated] (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - ISOTES, circa 1938-1939 (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - National Council, 1947-1960 (Box 10, Folder 111)
    - Nursing School
      - 1944-1946, [undated] (Box 10, Folder 112)
      - [no date] (Box 10, Folder 113)
    - Parapsychology Laboratory, 1935-1945, [undated] (Box 10, Folder 114)
    - (Department of) Physical Education for Women, 1931-1946, [undated] (Box 11, Folder 115)
    - Presbyterian Student Association, 1941-1945 (Box 11, Folder 116)
    - Schedule Committee, 1934-1942, [undated] (Box 11, Folder 117)
    - Sociology Department, "Marriage and Family" Course, 1934-1938 (Box 11, Folder 118)
    - Sororities
      - 1926-1942 (Box 11, Folder 119)
      - 1943-1946, [undated] (Box 11, Folder 120)
    - Trinity College Historical Society, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 121)
    - War Time Schedule, 1942-1943 (Box 11, Folder 122)
    - White Duchy, 1938-1948 (Box 11, Folder 123)
    - Woman's College
      - Admissions, circa 1954 (Box 11, Folder 124)
      - Debating Club, 1934-1939, [undated] (Box 11, Folder 125)
      - Dormitories, 1925-1933, [undated] (Box 11, Folder 126)
      - Faculty Minutes, 1932-1934 (Box 11, Folder 127)
      - Gifts, 1935-1942 (Box 11, Folder 128)
      - Health Committee, 1936-1942 (Box 11, Folder 129)
      - May Day Program, 1928-1938, [undated] (Box 11, Folder 130)
      - Miscellany (Box 12)
        - 1925-1933 (Box 12, Folder 131)
        - 1934-1958 (Box 12, Folder 132)
        - [undated] (Box 12, Folder 133)
      - Music Study Club, 1931-1945, [undated] (Box 12, Folder 134)